DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宫饭》
I'm so tired.
好累喔
All these stairs…
一直在走楼梯
doesn't it feel like you're twice as tired?
感觉疲倦感也加倍了对吧？
A moderate amount of fatigue makes your meal taste better.
适度的疲劳会让三餐更美味
In moderation, sure.
要适度才好啊
Give me your sword.
给我剑
Sure.
好
There should be a trick door around here.
这附近有机关
I almost forgot that the door led here.
差点忘了门是连通到这里
It saved us quite a bit of time.
节省了满多时间的耶
Huh?
奇怪
What is it?
怎么了？
The decoration on my sword guard is gone.
剑锷的雕饰不见了
It's because you were reckless with it.
谁叫你动作那么粗鲁
Was it my fault?
是我的错吗？
No, it was coming loose for a while now.
不 那从很久以前就已经松动了
I was trying to hold it together with string or glue,
我之前会用绳子固定 或用胶水黏起来应付一下
but I guess it was time.
但应该是撑不了了吧
Is there a problem if it's gone?
少了那个部分会有麻烦吗？
Nope. Not at all.
不 一点问题都没有
Was it a memento or something?
还是说那是充满回忆的物品？
A memento… I suppose you could say that.
充满回忆…那么说也没错啦
Three years ago, when I was just a beginner,
三年前 我还是个新手
I joined a gold-peeling crew to get some experience.
有一次我为了累积经验而加入剥金团
Gold-peeling?
剥金？
A long time ago, this castle was completely covered in gold,
以前这座城堡被金子所包覆
and peeling it made quite a profit.
剥下那些金子可以赚大钱
This place has been mostly peeled already.
这一带也几乎被人剥光了
Let's see if there's anything inside the castle.
我们去看看城堡里有没有什么东西吧
-Yes, sir.
-是
Laios, isn't it dangerous for us to enter the castle with our current abilities?
莱欧斯哥哥 凭我们的身手 进城堡内很危险吧？
Yeah, but the two of us can't turn back on our own.
是没错 不过光靠我们两个 无法独自回去啊
What the hell?
那是什么？
How awful.
太惨了
It's completely rotten away.
看来完全腐烂了
I guess that's what happens if you die in here.
万一死在这里 就不会被人发现
No one finds you.
最后落得这下场
Hey! Come over here!
喂 过来一下
You could probably sell these.
这应该卖得掉吧
They're better than what we saw earlier,
是比刚才的好多了
but you can only melt them down and sell them for ingredients…
但是只能融掉 赚点原料费…
T-The armor moved!
铠甲动起来了
It's a monster! Run!
是怪物 快逃啊
We're no match for it. Run!
我们打不过对方 快跑吧
You…!
你这家伙…
D-Dammit!
糟糕
My sword…
我的剑…
Come on…!
快点啊
I did it!
我办到了
-Laios! -Huh?
-莱欧斯哥哥 -怎么了？
Something like that happened.
以前发生过这样的事
And this is the sword I got then.
当时用的就是这把剑
So you lost…
你输了耶
It was my first death, so for a while, simply seeing an armor terrified me.
那是我第一次死亡 后来有一阵子看到铠甲都会怕
I read a lot of documents, but none of them described how they taste.
我读了各种文献 但是没有人写到铠甲的味道
I wonder what they taste like.
究竟会是什么样的味道呢？
Senshi, how would you cook them?
先西 你会怎么烹调铠甲？
Armor isn't edible.
铠甲又不能吃
Living Armor is simply controlled by magic, and it's not some creature.
会动的铠甲不是生物 只是受到魔法控制而已
I-I know that, but…
我是知道啦
What about the leather clasps?
但不是有一些扣环的皮革吗？
It's difficult to eat tanned hide,
鞣制皮革不易食用
and it's far easier to catch other monsters.
去抓其他魔物还比较轻松
If you're that hungry for armor, cook and eat your own.
你那么想吃铠甲的话 就煮自己穿的来吃吧
I see.
这样啊
I guess we can't eat Living Armor.
无法吃会动的铠甲啊
Come on, let's go.
好了 该走了
I'd rather not fight them now.
如果可以 现在真不想跟对方打
How about running our way past them?
要不要直接从旁边冲过去？
They're slow, so we could easily shake them off.
那些家伙跑得很慢 可以简单就甩开
True.
说的也是
Are you all okay with that?
你们可以做到吗？
Sure.
可以
We don't know which set of armor might move.
我们不知道哪一个铠甲会动
Everyone, be careful.
各位 千万要小心
Ready?
预备…
H-Here comes!
来了
Run!
快跑
Our way is completely blocked!
我们的去路完全被挡住了
What the heck?
怎么会这样？
H-Hey! This is bad!
天啊 情况不妙
Let's turn back for now and regroup!
我们先撤回去 重整队伍吧
Pull back!
撤退
They're especially persistent today.
今天那些家伙纠缠不休耶
I wonder if something put them in a bad mood.
是心情不好吗？
No way!
怎么可能
They don't have physical conditions or feelings.
那些魔物的身体状况或心情 根本就不分好坏
That's why it should be easy if we can defeat whoever is controlling them.
所以只要打倒操控者 事情就简单了
Are you sure there's someone?
真的有那号人物吗？
I've never seen them.
我从没见过
USUALLY
（平时）
Usually, they only attack anyone who gets close to them.
会动的铠甲平常只会攻击靠近的人类
But today, they clearly blocked our path.
但是今天却明显地阻挡我们的去路
In other words, maybe they're guarding something that's farther ahead.
换句话说 是不是可以推断 那些家伙是在守护前方的东西？
Whoever is controlling them is close by?
操控者就在附近？
You're right. That might be possible.
有道理 确实有可能
What? Is it a monster?
什么？是魔物吗？
I don't know.
不清楚
But a magic-user with such power can't be anyone decent!
不过能使用如此强力的魔法 绝对不是什么正派好人
Anyway, we have to find a way to get past that barrier of armor and…
总之我们要设法突破 那些铠甲的包围网 然后…
So, if we can reach the magic-user who is controlling the Living Armor,
所以只要能接触 操控会动的铠甲的魔法师
we might be able to stop them.
或许就能封住那些铠甲的动作
But how?
要怎么办？
For example…
比方说…
Three of us act as bait to draw their attention
三个人当诱饵 分散敌方的注意力
while one of us goes past the door.
剩下的一个人冲去门后面
Good luck.
加油了
I thought you might be the most fitting for the role
奇尔查克 你善于隐藏气息
since you're good at going unnoticed.
我觉得你最适合
I'm no good in combat.
我又不太会战斗
Besides, Living Armor doesn't have eyes or ears,
会动的铠甲没有眼睛跟耳朵
so going unnoticed doesn't help much against something that's not alive.
在非生物面前 隐藏气息没有任何意义吧
Doesn't have eyes or ears…
没有眼睛跟耳朵…
Are you ready?
准备好了吗？
All right! Let's go!
好 我们上吧
Come on!
看招
Gather around us, you sets of armor!
铠甲大军看过来 聚集吧
They're all coming!
来了一大堆
Don't panic!
别慌张
Aslam!
阿斯拉姆
What? There's another Living Armor here?
什么？这里也有会动的铠甲？
I've never seen this type of armor move.
我第一次看到这类型的铠甲动起来
I don't see anyone who's controlling it, though.
没看到操控者的身影
It looks stronger than the armor back there.
不过对方好像比外面的铠甲更强
I can't call for backup, though.
我没办法叫人支援
Anyway, I have to figure out on my own what they're guarding.
总之我得自己找出 这些铠甲在保护的东西
I'll cut off its arm or leg
我要先砍下手或脚
and render it immobile!
让对方动不了
Dammit! You…!
可恶 你这混蛋
Why did it guard its shield?
对方为何刚才要护住盾牌？
What's that?
那是什么？
There's something on its shield.
盾牌上有东西
Somehow, it seems very familiar.
感觉莫名地眼熟
Right.
对了
It's…
那是…
An egg case!
卵鞘
It's an egg of some creature.
是某种生物的卵
That's what it shielded!
对方是在保护那个
But what egg could it be?
不过那到底是什么的卵？
Is it the egg of whoever is controlling the armor?
是操控这些铠甲的人物的卵？
Besides, Living Armor doesn't have eyes or ears.
会动的铠甲没有眼睛跟耳朵
That's not it!
不对
It's been bugging me all this time.
我一直觉得怪怪的
They're inorganic, without eyes or ears.
没有眼睛与耳朵的无机物
The way they pick up their head and put it back on.
竟然会把头捡起来装回去
The way they turn their head and follow our movements.
还会转动脖子追踪我们的动作
And the egg…
还有卵…
There's no doubt about it! They're living creatures!
我确信了 会动的铠甲是生物
No one is giving them orders.
那些铠甲不是听从某人的命令
They're simply acting on their instincts and trying to protect the egg.
而是照本能行事 试图保护卵
In that case, there are many ways to defeat them!
既然如此 打倒对方的方法多的是
And…
然后…
they're edible!
这些家伙是可以吃的
This is endless!
没完没了啊
Are you serious?!
不会吧？
Don't pause! It's dangerous if you freeze!
不要停下来 静止不动很危险
Senshi! Behind you!
先西 小心后面
Aslam!
阿斯拉姆
Huh? Hey!
什么？等一下
Do they share parts?
是可以共享的部件吗？
What?!
什么？
Is that even possible?!
竟还可以那样？
Hey, Laios!
我说莱欧斯啊
Do something about these armors quickly!
快点解决这些铠甲啦
These Living Armors don't die even when you cut off their heads.
会动的铠甲就算被砍头也不会死
But if they're creatures, they must be killable.
但既然是生物就一定有办法杀掉
Either by internal injury, outflow of body fluid, suffocation, or starvation.
内脏损伤、体液外流、窒息、饿死
It's not realistic to try a method that takes time.
耗费时间的方法都不实用
First, I need to determine the form of the creature that is inside.
要先确定里面潜藏的生物的形状
For an amorphous creature like a Slime, its movements are too rigid.
以史莱姆这种形状不规则的 生物来说动作太有规律了
Is it possible that they're swarms of tiny creatures?
是小型生物的集合体吗？
But they don't make any sound, so that seems unlikely.
但是没有发出声音 所以不太可能
Or maybe creatures with long limbs are controlling them from inside.
或者是有手脚很长的生物 躲在里面操控？
They could be other creatures,
还有其他可能性
but it's probably easier to see for myself.
不过还是实际确认最快
It doesn't seem like I can match it in strength.
靠蛮力应该打不赢
In that case,
既然如此…
I only have one option!
就只有一个办法
Go for the shield with the egg attached, and make it drop its guard!
锁定附着卵的盾牌 制造破绽
Got it!
抢到了
What's inside? Huh?
里面有什么？怎么会？
There's nothing!
空无一物
It's empty.
空空如也
Could it have been a camouflage tactic when it retrieved its head?
难道铠甲会捡头回来只是拟态行为？
This is bad.
惨了
I need… I need to think of my next move!
我得赶快想出下一个对策
What?
什么？
Couldn't it see which pillar I hid behind?
对方没看到我躲在哪根柱子后面？
There must be something in its head, then.
果然是头部有什么东西？
A gap?
缝隙？
I see. It was a mollusk!
原来如此 是一种软体生物
It was clinging to the inside.
一直都附着在内侧啊
Could it have survived amputation
对方被砍断却依然没事
because it was a colony of many creatures to begin with?
是因为本来就是群生的个体吗？
Is it looking for its head?
那家伙是在找头吗？
Maybe in its current state…
也许现在的状态就可以…
Hmm, how interesting!
嗯 真有趣
Just how many are there?
到底有几只啊？
They mimic muscle movements
它们在关节处连接
by expanding and contracting at the joints.
通过伸缩运动模拟肌肉的动作啊
I wonder if they're hermaphrodites.
它们是雌雄同体吗？
I wonder which creature laid the egg.
产卵的不知道是哪个个体
I forgot I don't have time for this right now!
都忘了不是研究这些的时候
Excuse me!
不好意思啦
You…! Just let go!
你这混蛋 给我放手
Everyone! Come over here now!
大家 快过来这里
-Now's not the time!
-没空理你啦
Huh?
什么？
What was that? How did you do that?!
怎么回事？你是怎么办到的？
So there was a magic-user?!
果然有魔法师对吧？
There were no magic-users.
没有魔法师
The Living Armors weren't controlled.
没人在操控会动的铠甲
They were creatures.
它们本身便是生物
Huh?
什么意思？
Look at the inside of this armor.
你们看这铠甲的内部
There are two layers, and something is clinging between them.
内部是两层的构造 有东西攀附在夹层中间
This is the identity of the Living Armor.
这就是会动的铠甲的真面目
By clasping hands inside the armor,
它们在铠甲中手牵手
they were acting as muscles of different parts.
发挥各部位的肌肉功能
Even though each creature is weak,
虽然每一只都很脆弱
by dividing the body parts and utilizing the armor's structure,
但只要分别负责不同部位 再利用铠甲的外型构造
they can imitate human movements.
它们就能模仿人类的动作
Unluckily for us,
这次我们不太走运
it seems we encountered them during the spawning season this time.
好像是刚好碰到它们产卵的季节
Spawning?! These things hatch from eggs?!
产卵？它们是卵生的吗？
That's right! They hatch from eggs!
对 它们是从蛋里出生的
No one realized this until now!
至今为止都没人发现
Everyone thought they were simply Living Armor controlled by magic!
世人都以为只是 靠魔法活动的普通铠甲
If I were to reveal this fact, it would cause a huge stir in our circle!
把这件事公诸于世之后 会震撼业界吧
You know how he talks fast
那家伙聊到魔物的时候
when it comes to monsters?
语速就会变快
It creeps me out.
真恶心
Hush! Stop that.
嘘 别说了
Senshi!
先西
We might not be able to eat armor, but what about the stuff inside?
虽然铠甲不能吃 但内部的魔物如何？
Looks pretty nutritious, doesn't it?
看起来很有营养吧？
There's no way we can eat something so mysterious!
这么莫名其妙的东西哪能吃啊
Now, now, Marcille.
冷静点 玛露希尔
Every food is a mystery until that first bite.
不管是什么食物 在吃下第一口前都是谜团啊
Now's not the time to be trying it!
现在不该挑战这个吧？
Let's give it a shot.
来试试看吧
I'm using this ingredient for the first time,
这是老夫第一次碰到的食材
so I'm not confident, though.
虽然没什么自信啦
Thanks, Senshi.
谢谢你 先西
No way!
不要
What if it's extremely poisonous?
如果有剧毒怎么办？
I doubt a creature with potent poison would hide itself inside a shell.
毒性强的生物通常不会躲在壳里
But how should I cook it?
可是该怎么煮呢？
This underside…
这内侧啊…
didn't budge when I tried to pry it open with my hands.
想用手撬开的话完全动不了
But when I cut this part with a blade, it couldn't close the gap.
但是用刀切这部分 缝隙就合不起来了
Maybe it was an adductor muscle that it uses to close the gap,
应该是让缝隙闭合时用到的闭壳肌吧
like a scallop.
可能像是贝柱
I see. So it's a shellfish.
原来如此 所以是贝类啊
All right, I've decided.
好 决定了
Pry the meat from the armor, will you?
你们帮忙从铠甲剥肉下来吧
It drowned.
溺水了
I guess you can't purge the sand with water.
看来没办法泡水吐沙呢
I don't know if they even need to be purged of sand.
老夫也不知道它需不需要吐沙
I'm a bit worried about their internal organs,
因为比较担心里头的器官
so I'll remove them.
所以切除内脏
The sliced meat will go inside a soup.
在切片后煮汤
Oil, meat from the Living Armor, herbs, and seasoning.
倒油后放入会动的铠甲肉片 以及药草和调味料
And the head…
至于头部…
will be steamed.
就焖熟吧
And finally, we might as well make the classic dish.
最后一道就做成经典的料理
It's ready!
完成了
DWARF-STYLE LIVING ARMOR STIR-FRY LIVING ARMOR SOUP
（矮人风会动的铠甲炒菜 会动的铠甲汤）
GRILLED LIVING ARMOR
（会动的铠甲烧烤）
STEAM-BAKED LIVING ARMOR
（会动的铠甲焖肉）
Marcille, which do you want to have first?
玛露希尔 你要先吃哪道？
What?
什么？
I-I'll have the soup, then…
那我要先喝汤…
Wait, do antidotes work against food poisoning as well?
等等 解毒药对食物中毒也有效吗？
It doesn't smell bad.
气味还满香的
It smells faintly of iron.
闻起来有淡淡的铁味
Laios,
莱欧斯
here.
给你
It's hot!
好烫
Why are you all looking at me like that?
为什么大家都要用那种眼神看我？
You've been craving Living Armor for a long time now, right?
吃会动的铠甲不是你的宿愿吗？
We shouldn't eat it before you do.
我们可不能比你早吃
I see…
也对呢
If he dies, let's leave him here.
他要是死了 就把他丢在这里吧
Yeah.
好
-Did he die?
-他死了？
It's delicious!
好吃
What on earth? It's so delicious!
这是什么啊？超好吃
At first, it tasted bland, but the flavor kicks in later!
一开始还以为没味道 但随后味道就涌上来了
How long does it take before you start having symptoms of food poisoning?
出现食物中毒的症状要等多久？
It depends on the food.
要看吃的是什么
So that's what it tastes like.
原来是这种味道啊
Not bad, but I think I could've cooked it better.
还不错 但老夫可以煮得更美味
How about the dish you have?
你们那道料理味道如何？
Well, I suppose this one should be safe because it was stir-fried with herbs.
不过跟药草一起炒应该是安全的吧
H-How is it?
怎么样？
It's not bad.
不难吃
What do you think, Marcille?
怎么样啊 玛露希尔？
It tastes a bit like mushrooms.
有种香菇的味道
Right?
对吧？
The steam-baked one looks ready and tasty, too.
焖烤料理也做得很成功
It has to taste great!
不用想也知道一定好吃
It tastes like mold.
有一股霉味
The odor of the helmet must've gotten trapped in it.
可能把头盔的味道焖在里面了
Here.
给你
You know, I've been in the dungeon for a long time now,
老夫在迷宫待了很长一段时间
but I never thought they were edible.
万万没想到这家伙竟然可以吃
Nobody would expect Living Armor to be a sort of shellfish
会动的铠甲其实是 类似贝类的卵生魔物
that hatch from eggs.
一般人都想不到吧
Maybe when they're newborns and juveniles, they're very small,
刚出生的幼体一定很小
and no one suspects them to be Living Armor.
所以没人会联想到是会动的铠甲
They probably form shells as they grow.
它们可能是在成长期长出外壳
Then, they start forming colonies.
接着组成群体
And when they can move, they travel looking for other colonies.
变得能够动之后再移动去找其他群体
Maybe the armor standing in rows were looking for partners.
排成一列的铠甲 也许是在相亲找对象呢
They are likely hermaphrodites and the biggest colony lays an egg.
它们可能是雌雄同体 群体中最大的个体负责产卵
Oh! That means…
天啊 也就是说…
The armor I occasionally see holding hands
我们时不时会看到铠甲牵着手
might not have been adventurers fooling around.
那可能不是冒险者的恶作剧
Maybe they were actually mating!
而是在交配啊
You can drop it now.
够了啦
To think the thing I was so scared of for a time
我有一段时期这么惧怕对方
was such a tasty and feeble monster.
没想到它们是如此美味且弱小的魔物
Your sword broke, huh?
你的剑断了啊？
Why don't you take that one?
你就带走那把如何？
Laios!
莱欧斯
If you're going to use that sword, shall I test it to see if it's not cursed?
你要用那把剑的话 要我帮你鉴定有没有被诅咒吗？
No need!
没关系
I'm absolutely sure it's not cursed!
一定没有被诅咒
I can tell!
我能看得出来
You seem awfully confident.
哪来的自信啊？
Don't come to me if you end up with some weird curse.
你要是被奇怪的诅咒缠上 我可不会管你喔
Everyone, wait for me!
大家 等等我
Armed with a new sword,
获得了新剑后
their journey continues.
他们继续展开旅程
The other three had no way of knowing
然后还多了一个伙伴
that they had a new companion.
但其他三人对此毫不知情
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻译：梁雪莹